Sorry, Rocco.
Come, come.
Good dog.
Somali Al-Shabab militants have posted
this picture of an unnamed man
they say they have executed in Nairobi.
They claim he was a spy working for
British and Kenyan intelligence services,
attempting to disrupt the recruiting
and trafficking of young Western Muslims.
Al-Shabab extremism within Kenya escalated
with the Westgate shopping mall attack
in Nairobi two years ago,
in which 67 people died
and 175 were injured.
In April, the group massacred
147 students and staff
at Garissa University College.
Al-Shabab want to
impose their strict version
of Sharia law across the Horn of Africa.
They bitterly resent the role
of Britain and the Kenyan military
in propping up the UN-backed
Somali government.
- Morning, Colonel.
- Morning, Ted.
Good morning.
- Good morning, ma'am.
- Morning, Colonel.
Version three on Operation Egret is ready.
Ahmed's house data is on slide three.
Thank you.
Only two Hellfires? Where are my GBU-12s?
Well, ma'am, given the mission brief,
we thought we should
decrease the gross weight
and increase the loiter time.
So I've only got the Hellfires?
Yes, ma'am.
Sadd, next time you change the load out,
you check with me first, please?
- Yes, ma'am.
- Thank you.
How was your flight?
General, good morning.
You got my email?
Yes, sir. Very upsetting.
His family will need our support.
Leave it with me.
- Everything in place?
- Yes, sir.
I'll be at Cobra in an hour.
That should be fine.
Good luck today, Katherine.
Thank you.
Is this Briefing Room 7?
Yeah. You're fine. We haven't started yet.
Lieutenant Watts.
Airman Gershon.
Pleasure.
Stand by.
Room, attention.
Carry on.
All right, I'm going to introduce you
guys to Colonel Powell in London.
- Push us through please, Major.
- Yes, sir.
Good morning, Colonel.
Are we coming through clear?
Loud and clear, Colonel, thank you.
Good to see you again.
And you, ma'am. I have your crew ready.
Introduce yourselves, please.
Morning, ma'am. Lieutenant Steve Watts,
Aircraft Commander, Pilot.
Airman First Class Carrie Gershon,
Sensor Operator.
Senior Airman Matt Levery,
Mission Intel Coordinator.
Thank you.
Today, you will be flying a joint
operation over Nairobi, Kenya,
codename Operation Egret.
Horn of Africa, Somalia, Kenya, Nairobi.
We have intelligence of a meeting
of key members of Al-Shabab
in the suburb of Parklands
in this house, here.
It belongs to a man named Shahid Ahmed.
He's an Al-Shabab facilitator.
Due to visit this house is this man,
Abdullah Al-Hady.
He's a Somali, and his wife,
Ayesha Al-Hady,
formerly Susan Helen Danford,
British national.
Troubled childhood, converted at 15.
She was radicalized in a West London mosque
where she met and married Al-Hady.
Intelligence has them connected to
the most recent suicide bombing in Kenya.
They are numbers four and five
on our East Africa Most Wanted list.
We've been tracking them for six years.
Their cell executed one of
our Kenyan agents yesterday.
Now we have information
that they will be in Nairobi today,
using that Parklands house
as a transit point for two new recruits.
Muhammad Abdisalaam, American.
The CIA have him connected
to extremists in Minnesota.
And Rasheed Hamud. He's British.
Once all suspects are in the house,
Kenyan special forces will launch
a cordon and search.
This is an operation to capture, not kill.
Your job is to be their eye in the sky.
Right, thank you, ma'am. Kill it.
- Yes, sir.
- Go brief.
So, sir, how long have you been here?
About six months now. You?
Just got here.
Oh, wow. How are you liking Vegas?
It can get a little wild.
That it can.
Where are you from originally?
- I'm from Ohio.
- Ohio?
Where are you... Where are you from?
Idaho. When did you qualify?
A month ago.
Wow. It's only been
about two years for me.
Why'd you join?
I'd racked up a lot of college debt.
Air Force was a guaranteed
four years of work.
- Hey, guys.
- Hi.
- Hey.
You seen any giraffes?
Matter of fact, yeah.
- Oh, wow.
- Yeah, a whole bunch of them
about 30 miles east of the city.
The aircraft is established in the orbit
at Flight Level 200, running covert.
Aircraft and GCS are in the green
with no write-ups.
Okay. Great.
All cameras checked good.
Here's the target.
Ground forces are a few blocks
away in an old factory.
Over here.
Okay. Thanks.
Weapons all spun up good.
Ten hours' time on station remaining.
You still have two Hellfire missiles.
Secure radio checked good.
Great. Thank you, guys.
All right. Do good. Don't suck.
Hey, Matt? You strapped in?
I'm here. Here it comes.
Showman 5-0, North 2-0.
Good morning, Moses. How are you?
North 2-0, Showman 5-0.
Good morning, Colonel. Very good, thank you.
Confirm Seahawk is in the Blue Zone,
but Condor is still in flight, right?
Seahawk is in the Blue Zone.
We expect Condor to land in an hour.
Thank you. Are your men in place?
Yes, ma'am.
Darling, it's your dad here.
I'm looking at a whole shelf
of these Annabell dolls.
You didn't tell me that
there were different types.
I have no idea what to buy her.
Can you get back to me ASAP?
Otherwise...
Um...
I'm holding a "Time to Sleep" doll.
It says here, "You will hear her babbling
"when it is beddy-byes."
Call me as soon as you can.
General Benson here for Cobra.
General Benson.
Jack Cleary. I'm coordinating today.
- This way, sir.
- Thank you.
Hold on a minute. "Baby Moves"?
What have I got?
Well, does it matter? I mean...
General, they're asking for you, sir.
Yes. Uh... All right, darling, I'll try.
Yup. Bye-bye.
I bought a "Time to Sleep" doll
when I should have bought a "Baby Moves."
Apparently,
there's an important difference.
I'll see what I can do, sir.
- Attorney General, good morning.
- Good morning, Frank.
- Minister.
- General.
Ma'am.
Congratulations on your new appointment.
Thank you.
I'm gonna talk you through
the capture of Susan Danford,
AKA Ayesha Al-Hady.
- How are you?
- I'm good, and you?
Welcome to Nairobi.
The Condor has landed.
Copy that. Proceed to the Blue Zone.
- Hey.
- Did you go to the game?
- I was busy.
You might still make it.
What have we got here?
Tracking some extremists in Nairobi.
One guy's from my hometown.
You're kidding. Serious?
- Yup. Uh-huh.
- Is that him?
Muhammad Abdisalaam, Somali.
A lot of them there.
Well, let's hope he's not coming back.
- Yeah. Have a good shift.
- Thanks.
- Thank you.
- Mmm-hmm.
What's going on?
We've got Condor in the Blue Zone.
Who the fuck is Condor?
The second guy in from the airport.
I can't keep up with these names.
Showman 5-0, can we get
a view into the house?
Peg 9-0, Showman 5-0,
can you try and look into the house?
Moving now.
Showman 50, would you
like us to bring in Ringo?
Negative. Wait for number three to arrive.
We have movement.
Damn it. Are they leaving?
Where are Danford and Al-Hady?
Colonel, our intelligence only has them
arriving in another half hour.
Well, then our intelligence is bad.
Load up!
North 2-0, Showman 5-0,
I have my men ready. Do we go in?
No, no, no. No, Major, please.
Hold your men. I want Danford.
Copy. Halt! Hold up!
Halt!
Bravo 2-7, follow if they leave.
Hawaii 5, confirm PID.
Roger, North 2-0. I'd like to be closer.
Peg 9-0, go closer for PID.
North 2-0, Hawaii 5
confirms positive IDs on
Muhammad Abdisalaam and Rasheed Hamud.
Roger that.
- Who's that?
- Zoom in.
Is that Danford?
I need a PID.
Shit.
Damn it. Is that her,
or does Ahmed have a wife?
I'm sorry, Colonel, we don't know.
No, not good enough, people.
It has to be her.
Why didn't we know she was
already in the house?
Movers, say intentions.
- Stay on PAX.
- Copy.
Bravo 2-7 following.
Hawaii 5, I want a PID on that woman
as soon as we get a visual.
Yes, ma'am.
Zoom out.
North 2-0. Showman 5-0.
Looks like they're heading
towards Eastleigh.
So, how do we launch a ground
assault if she's going in there?
We can't. Al-Shabab
controls that neighborhood.
It would trigger a massacre.
All right. All right, just...
Just stay with her.
Showman 50, Bravo 27.
It's too risky to follow.
Return to base.
Showman 5-0, do we know this house?
It belongs to Amadu Mukhtar.
He's a Somali trader,
but there is no other intel on him.
Oh, shit.
Hawaii 5, North 2-0.
Did you see anything there?
- No, ma'am.
- Shit.
Showman 5-0, we need an eye
inside that house.
I have to know if Danford is inside,
and who is with her.
Ma'am, it would mean putting
a man in the street,
and you'd have to get close
to control the beetle.
It would easily raise suspicion.
What, even if you use a Somali?
Every stranger is
suspicious, even a Somali.
Moses, we both believe that Danford
is inside that house, do we not?
Yes, ma'am.
And I cannot authorize a strike
without a positive ID.
I believe we have to accept
the risk and send someone in.
Moses, can you do it?
Yes, ma'am.
Thank you. Appreciate what you're doing.
Peg 9-0, Showman 5-0.
I need you to engage Ringo
at the target house.
We need a positive ID.
Okay.
- Thanks, man.
- Mmm-hmm.
What?
Alia.
What's that?
Get Ringo around the other side
to identify the woman.
That's Danford.
Hawaii 5, confirm PID, please.
PID, Susan Helen Danford.
We have Danford.
But we can't enter
the militia-controlled area.
No.
What's the plan, General?
Well, using the Reaper,
we have the ability
to strike a target with
considerable accuracy.
If you agree, Minister,
we could eliminate her.
Absolutely not!
Ma'am, she's a member of Al-Shabab
and number four on our East African
Most Wanted list.
I don't care about your list, General.
I came here to witness a capture,
not a targeted assassination.
George.
Yes, I'm sorry, Frank.
I agree with Angela.
The idea was to capture
Danford, not kill her.
This was the mission approved by the PM.
And, as Attorney General,
that is what I came here to witness.
We want her brought back
to this country to stand trial.
Right.
I'll put that to Colonel Powell.
What's happening?
I don't know.
Hey, Matt, what's going on?
We got a beetle inside that house, and we're
seeing a bunch of people we don't like.
That's him. That's her husband.
Hawaii 5, confirm.
Showman 5-0, we've got them both.
Yes, ma'am. This is wonderful.
I need Peg 9-0 to take me
into the other rooms.
Shit.
Oh, fuck, man.
- Fuck. Fuck.
- Matt, what's happening?
We're seeing suicide vests and a whole bunch
of fucking explosives inside that house.
Well, this changes things.
All right. Keep it calm,
okay? Don't wind up my pilot.
I want legal in here right now.
Yes, ma'am.
They're gonna make a suicide video.
Who is that, Colonel?
Looks like Osman Abade.
He supplied the explosives
in the Lamu bombing.
What's the plan, Katherine?
We need to put a Hellfire
through that roof right now.
I told you, they came
to witness a capture, not a kill.
Give me a capture option.
We no longer have a capture option.
Any action on the ground will lead
to an armed confrontation,
which we will not be able to contain.
They're watching.
Even with the vests, we need
their approval for a strike.
Just tell them we've got
Danford in our sights.
I mean, that alone should
justify using a Hellfire.
The vests are just a bonus.
Danford's a British citizen.
They want her alive.
They cannot have her alive!
Frank, I've tracked her for six years.
This is the closest I've ever got.
So, we need to expand our rules
of engagement right now
to protect the civilian population.
A Hellfire through that roof
is our most effective option.
We have to know
that we're legally in the clear.
Yes. Yes, of course.
I'm getting into that right now.
Colonel?
- Oh, Harold, you've been following?
- Yes, ma'am.
So, the plan is to put a Hellfire
through the roof of that house.
I need legal clearance right now.
- A missile from the Reaper?
- Yes.
So, this is no longer a capture situation.
No. We have two suicide vests
with explosives inside that house.
So, can you clear me to a higher CDE?
Uh...
Harold, this is a very time-sensitive target.
Do I have authority to strike?
The rules of engagement
you're operating under
only allow for a low
collateral damage estimate.
Yes, yes, and my weapons
only invoke a low CDE.
It's the explosives inside that house
that bring it to a potentially high CDE.
And since you know
the explosives are there,
it is incumbent upon you
to take them into account.
I can see a potential legal objection.
Jesus! We've got two suicide bombers
and three very high value
individuals inside that house!
And you want them off your list,
I understand that.
But the rules of engagement
you're operating under
envisaged a capture, not a kill scenario.
Ma'am, I think it
would be wise to refer up.
Are you telling me that,
or just debating with me?
To refer up?
Mmm-hmm.
- I am telling you.
- Oh!
- Benson.
- Sir.
Legal has advised me to refer up
to the Attorney General.
I need a quick answer, Frank.
Okay, I'll put that to him.
George.
Those explosives mean
there is an imminent threat
of serious harm to
the civilian population.
Can we strike?
Well, given the new circumstances,
I would say yes.
Brian.
There is a political as well
as a legal call to be made here.
Yes, I'm quite aware of that, George.
We need a decision now, Minister.
Legally, we don't have a problem?
No, we don't.
But politically...
Do we have permission to proceed?
Well,
- you seem to be implying yes, George.
- Thank you.
- Hold on a minute. Hold on.
- No. That is not what I...
This is a change of mission from
a capture to a shoot-to-kill, isn't it?
Yes, it is.
Are we all right with that?
I'm sure we are not.
There are two British citizens
and an American as targets.
This mission has the full support
of Kenya and the United States.
For a drone strike?
Yes, a missile fired from an RPA
is part of an agreed contingency plan
in circumstances like this.
Do we have permission to proceed?
No. Such a plan should not
have been signed off by the PM
without the authority of Parliament.
Operational issues are not
generally discussed at Cabinet,
and certainly not at Parliament.
I know the protocol. I'm talking
about what should be happening.
Angela, in my view, all the legal criteria
for an attack have been met.
Namely, this is a military necessity,
there is no reasonable alternative,
and the force to be used
is in proportion to the threat.
That should answer your question.
It does not, George.
Has there ever been a British-led
drone attack on a city
in a friendly country that is not at war?
General?
I do not believe so, no.
Then how can we sanction it?
Generate new damage rings for the compound
with an assessment of the payload
on those jackets.
- Yes, ma'am.
- Right now.
- Colonel Walsh.
- Colonel.
Can I speak to your pilot directly?
Yes, ma'am. Patch me through.
Steve.
Colonel Powell wants to talk
to you directly. Pick up.
Ma'am.
Lieutenant.
You are now our best option
to take these HVis out.
Now, prepare to launch a single
AGM-114 Hellfire on the target house.
- Yes, ma'am.
- This is a friendly city,
so collateral damage
must be kept to a minimum.
- Ma'am...
- Yes?
I have an ROE question.
Is my government aware that we are
targeting a person with a US passport?
Yes. Yes, it is, Lieutenant.
I didn't see anything
in the SPINS about that.
Lieutenant, we have
new rules of engagement.
You are covered.
This is going to happen fast,
so be ready to shoot.
Yes, ma'am.
Running the dash 34 checklist.
Carrie, call when ready.
You ever shot a Hellfire?
No.
Or anything?
No. I've only ever been the eye.
You?
Me, too.
Looks like it's your
lucky day today, guys.
Just stay cool, okay? Be all right.
Yes, sir.
Carrie, call when ready.
Slant range 22,000 feet.
High-impact angle.
Stand by for targeting brief.
Ready.
Angela, I agree,
we are at risk of being perceived
as embarking on a shoot-to-kill policy.
But since all the legal
criteria are sound,
I believe we must allow
this military action to continue.
Legally we may be safe, but politically
we're walking into a minefield.
Especially with
an American citizen involved.
Do I have permission, Minister?
Um...
Given the situation,
that it is a change of mission,
that it is now a missile attack
on a British subject,
two British subjects,
and an American citizen,
and in a friendly country,
I think it is only right and proper
that I refer this up to
the Foreign Secretary.
Minister, you've heard
the arguments, he hasn't.
And the rules of engagement mean that
the Prime Minister
has already approved it.
- No...
- Therefore,
the Foreign Secretary's input
should not be rendered...
No, the point is that
I have not been party
to any previous discussion
with the Prime Minister
about matters such as this, whereas
the Foreign Secretary undoubtedly has.
So, actually, it is my
duty to refer to him.
And what am I telling Colonel Powell?
Tell her to wait!
Oh, Christ Almighty!
Thank you.
As a member of the British government,
I am proud to introduce
Integrated Battlefield Solutions,
a UK company leading the field
in the production
of life-saving,
lightweight military clothing.
Protecting our soldiers
in the field of battle
is at the core of my government's
commitment to our armed forces.
"Soldier safety first" is why we're in...
Excuse me.
Oh, God, he's gonna throw up!
I told him not to eat the prawns.
Excuse me.
And so I'm very pleased to introduce you
to IBS Managing Director
Mr. Nigel Adler.
Thank you very much, Foreign Secretary.
Today we're introducing the Adamant
Assault Body Armor System.
- Do we have that CDE yet?
- Yes, ma'am.
Good.
If we target this corner room here,
where the explosives are,
we would expect 100%
mortality rate in that room
and an 80 to 90% rate
within the rest of the house.
The market should be safe,
but this area here in the street...
A 65 to 75% rate.
That's just the Hellfire.
If we factor in
the explosives in the vests,
we're looking at even more extensive
damage way out to this area here.
But I can't accurately
estimate that yield.
But we would be containing
that payload in the vests
within those walls, right?
Far less collateral damage than them
going off in a crowded shopping mall.
Yes. Of course.
Yeah. Thank you.
Obvious to anyone not trying
to avoid making a decision.
The meeting with the Malaysian Trade
Minister is now at 4:30.
You'll have to do it for me.
But, sir, the whole
point of us being here...
Yeah, maybe if you take an Eezi Tum.
Look. I need to go back to the hotel now.
Jack, what's the holdup?
I'm sorry, sir, I'm trying to reach him.
Minister, the consequences of delay
may be fatal to scores of civilians.
I'm well aware of that, General,
but it is the proper procedure
for me to seek his approval.
If these men leave now,
in separate vehicles...
There are two vehicles outside,
we have the ability to follow only one.
We have only one eye in the sky.
Surely you have agents on the ground
who could intercept?
Intercept a suicide
bomber on a city street?
We're trying to
minimize collateral damage.
Showman 5-0, North 2-0.
When I give the order to attack, you have
to get your man out of there immediately.
He'll have about three minutes.
Understood.
We are greened up.
Missile status is ready.
Left selected for single fire,
coded and ready.
Stand by.
You're cleared to test the laser.
Laser on. Good laser.
Oh, come on, sir.
We need a go. They ain't gonna
be in that house forever.
Just keep it together, all right?
Yes, sir.
We need a decision, Minister.
Right now.
Thank you. Thank you.
I have the Foreign Secretary.
Mmm-hmm?
It's Brian on your phone.
- Brian who?
- Woodale.
What does he want?
I can't talk to him now.
It's urgent. He's at Cobra.
The checklist is complete.
Safety checklist complied with.
Desired point of impact is captured.
ROE is pending.
We're standing by for clearance.
Gentlemen, I cannot authorize
a missile attack on an American citizen
without the approval of
the US Secretary of State.
Sir, the Secretary of State is in China.
Then track him down.
Foreign Secretary,
it's General Benson here.
With respect,
this has already been cleared
at American Presidential level.
We have a situation here which
could result in massive loss of life
in the next 10 minutes.
Then use those 10 minutes
and get the Secretary's approval.
That is my decision, General.
I'll get onto the Embassy in Beijing.
I'd better speak to him. Excuse me.
- Kate. Get me linked in on my laptop.
- Sir?
- Yes, sir.
- Got it.
Oh!
Okay, that was embarrassing. Sorry.
- Ready?
- Just give me a second.
Mr. Secretary, I have
Jordan Ricardo on the line.
Who?
Jordan Ricardo,
from our embassy here in Beijing.
It's urgent.
I'm so sorry.
Sir, we've received a call from
the British regarding an operation.
Why the hell are you wasting
my time referring this to me?
No, his citizenship does not protect him.
By joining Al-Shabab he has declared
himself an enemy of the United States.
Listen to me.
Tell the British, if they really do have
two, four, and five on the East Africa
list in their sights,
they have our full support to strike.
Yes, all three are on
the President's list.
Okay, let's go! Yeah!
I'm gonna get you, Jian.
The Secretary of State
has given his permission.
You may proceed.
Thank you, Minister.
Oh!
Thank you.
Ma'am.
Lieutenant, you have clearance
to prosecute the target.
Do it now.
Yes, ma'am.
Prepare to launch Hellfire.
I think I'm through the worst of it.
What's happening?
The Secretary gave his permission.
They have a Reaper at 20,000 feet
and a micro RPA inside the house.
Weapon is armed.
All green. Good laser.
DPI is the center of the room.
Copy. Crosshairs on it now.
Stand by.
- Confirm PAX status.
- All good.
Good luck.
Three.
Two.
Is that a kid? Zoom in.
I'll give her time to walk through.
Ma'am?
You are cleared to engage, Lieutenant.
She stopped.
Lieutenant, we have this one opportunity.
Let's not lose it.
Ma'am, uh, she's selling bread.
Jesus.
Those men are about to disperse.
Engage now.
Ma'am, I understand we have clearance.
I will fire if I see the HVis moving
or when this girl's out of the frag radius,
but I want to give her a chance
to get out of the way.
Lieutenant, you have clearance.
There is a lot more at stake
than you see here in this image.
Ma'am, I need you to run
the collateral damage estimate
again with this girl out front.
The situation has not changed, Lieutenant.
You are cleared to engage.
What do we do?
I repeat, you are cleared to engage.
Colonel Powell, ma'am...
I'm the pilot in command responsible
for releasing the weapon.
I have the right to ask
for the CDE to be run again.
I will not release my weapon
until that happens.
We will rerun CDE.
Fuck.
Do I understand
we are now on "weapons hold"?
Weapons hold.
- Sergeant, rerun CDE.
- Yes, ma'am.
Steve, what the fuck are you doing?
You just threw the rule book at a colonel.
Sir, I am safing up the weapon until you
read me a new clearance with a new CDE.
Well done.
Showman 5-0, North 2-0, can you get
your man with a beetle in there
to buy this girl's bread,
get her out of there?
Shit!
Fuck!
Can you get me back to the house?
Yes, Colonel.
Carrie, forget him.
Get back to the target.
Carrie.
Back to the target.
Jesus, she's gonna sell them again.
Who else can we get to buy the bread?
Forget the bread, Sergeant.
We'll be lucky if our man
hasn't blown the whole operation.
Harold, where are we legally?
- With the girl?
- Yes.
- Are we in the clear?
- Uh...
Again, I would refer up.
No. No. I'm asking you.
We cannot hold up this
operation any longer.
We need to take all reasonable steps
to minimize collateral damage.
If we're buying her bread then...
We're not.
We're not buying her bread. That's over.
Many children's lives are at risk.
This is just one girl.
Are we clear to engage, yes or no?
Come on, make a decision.
With respect, ma'am,
I don't make those decisions.
I'm here to advise you on the law!
The law is not here to get in your way,
it is here to protect you,
and to protect your target.
Don't lecture me, Harold!
Ma'am, the legal questions of necessity and
proportionality are almost certainly met.
But for the protection of you,
and for the protection of that girl,
I would refer up to the Attorney General.
Benson.
Frank, may I speak to the Attorney General?
Connect us to Colonel Powell.
George.
She wants to talk to you.
Go ahead, Katherine.
Sir, our lawyer says the girl's presence
has not necessarily altered
the legitimacy of our operation.
But he does need that confirmed.
Do we have an assessment
of what might happen to her?
The targeteer assesses a 65 to 75% chance
of fatal injury should we proceed.
But he has also assessed
a projected loss of life
of up to 80 men, women and children
if the vests are
detonated in an urban area.
Now that's a guess, of course,
but we should assume they intend
to target a crowded location.
A 65% assessment requires us
to do whatever we can
to enable her to be
removed from the scene.
We have done what we can for her
in the time available to us.
If we wait and they leave,
we will no longer have
control of the situation.
We must strike now.
There is no law covering
a situation quite like this.
It's one thing to release a missile
whilst the street is clear
in the hope that it will remain so.
It's quite another thing knowing that
this girl will,
at worst, be fatally injured
and, at best, severely injured.
So, I'm sorry, I disagree with the
assessment of your lawyer at Northwood.
Agreed.
I hope the fact that she's a sweet little
girl is not clouding your judgment.
Dozens of other little girls' lives
are at stake if these men leave.
I'm sorry, but we have a Miss Jillian
Goldman from the White House
asking to be patched in.
- Who?
- Jillian Goldman.
She's a Senior Legal Adviser
at the US National Security Council.
She's been briefed by
the Secretary of State.
Put her through.
Good afternoon and thank you
for allowing me to comment.
Yeah, thanks for joining us.
As the military members
of your committee know,
we have a point system that takes
into account collateral damage
to deduce what is and
what is not a legal strike.
And let me tell you categorically that
the existence of this new circumstance
does not push us beyond
a legitimate military action.
We are way off what we would
consider a dispute in this matter.
Miss Goldman, we have
a somewhat different approach
to the question of collateral damage.
Sir, you must act now. You have two men
about to embark on a suicide mission.
You have number two, four, and five
on the President's East Africa
kill list in your sights,
and you are putting the whole mission at risk
because of one collateral damage issue?
I realize that this mission is your call,
but there would be some mighty angry people
here at the White House and at the
Pentagon, and out there in the world
if you allow these people to leave
and blow a shopping mall to kingdom come.
I'm sorry. We have the Foreign
Secretary wanting to join.
Right. We appreciate
your thoughts, Miss Goldman.
Thank you.
Good afternoon, everybody.
Excuse my appearance.
It's night here, and I have
a bout of food poisoning.
Sorry to drag you from your sick bed.
That's quite all right.
George, do I understand this correctly?
There's a legal argument for waiting and
giving this girl a chance to sell her bread?
Yes, there is.
But, conversely, it does not mean
that there is not also a legal argument
for releasing the weapon now.
Forgive me, I'm not sure that helps me.
Foreign Secretary, there is a military
necessity for acting now.
In our view, they'll be making a move
from that house at any moment.
Gentlemen, what action is being
legally recommended to me?
James, the legal argument
is that we could wait,
but we need not wait.
And the military argument
is that we should not wait.
- Right?
- Exactly.
It's my recommendation
that we should not delay
in proceeding with this mission.
If we don't act now, we risk losing
the lives of up to 80 people.
You can only assume those deaths.
What is certain is that if we do
act now, this one girl will suffer.
And you would save her
and risk killing 80 others?
Yes, I would save her and take that risk.
That is what I would do.
Angela, is it you or me who will
be invited onto the Today program
to explain why we knew of the attack
on a shopping center that killed 80 people,
but chose to do nothing to stop it?
You, James.
But frankly, politically,
I'd rather point to Al-Shabab
as murderers of 80 people shopping
than have to defend a drone attack
by our forces that
kills an innocent child.
James, Angela makes a compelling point.
If Al-Shabab kill 80 people,
we win the propaganda war.
If we kill one child, they do.
So, we don't do it?
She's got a customer.
I suggest you keep your eyes
on the other screen.
With respect, Foreign Secretary,
are the lives of 80 people,
including innocent children,
really worth the price
of winning the propaganda war?
General, if we go ahead,
might footage of our attack be leaked?
Sir, the footage from the Reaper
is completely secure.
General, I would feel uncomfortable
if we did not at least wait a little longer.
If we go ahead and footage
is leaked and this girl is killed,
then, I think, the country
would be most disturbed.
Foreign Secretary, it is our task
to make the right military decision.
We cannot engage in an argument about
possible future postings on YouTube.
With respect, General, revolutions
are fueled by postings on YouTube.
I think the consequences are such
that we need clearance from the PM.
James! You have the authority
to make a decision!
No, I'm telling you.
You need to take it to him.
Sir, the PM is giving a speech
in Strasbourg this afternoon,
and may not be easily interrupted.
I'll leave you to sort that one out, Jack.
Yes, sir.
I'll track him down.
Yes?
Ma'am, what's happening?
You're on standby, Lieutenant.
Yes, ma'am.
Still on the chain.
Two loaves left.
We gotta wait now.
Come on.
Ma'am, the battery died.
Our man is down. We can't replace it.
Christ.
- What happened?
- Battery.
Oh, for God's sake!
Now we have no idea what they're doing.
I might have a solution.
If my targeteer can calculate us
coming in under 50%
for collateral damage on the girl,
do you think you can get
approval at your end?
Yes, I do.
Thanks.
Battery.
Sergeant Saddiq, we're looking
to present the collateral damage
in the street, in this area right here,
as 45 to 50% fatality.
Do you think that's possible?
I've calculated a 65 to 75.
Yes, yes. Sure, sure, but, you know,
if we put the payload here, or here,
or maybe here,
well, then we could guarantee
the target fatality,
but we could reduce the collateral.
Or maybe we could target
the missile right here, look.
Yes, ma'am.
Will you just...
You just do whatever
you can to save this girl's life.
I'll leave it with you.
Yes, ma'am.
If we have to announce
to the people of Nairobi
that we knew everything but did nothing...
We do not have to announce
that we knew anything, General.
The PM asks that we do what we
can to minimize casualties.
- Bloody coward!
- What do you think we're doing?
How do you interpret that, George?
Minister, we cannot have military decisions
dictated by government committees.
Nor can we put on hold a military operation
at every stage for legal clarification.
You tell us when to go to war, we conduct
the war, you deal with the aftermath.
If only it were that simple.
Sorry to rush you, Sergeant,
but we don't have much time.
Yes, ma'am.
Ma'am.
Adjusting the point of impact to here...
- - Mmm-hmm.
there is a 45 to 65%
possibility of fatality.
- 65%?
- Yes.
No, I need that calculation
to be below 50%.
Perhaps there could be an assessment of
the impact of the damage right here.
That calculation is already at the lowest
limit of what I believe is possible.
What if you put the missile there?
I would still have to make that
a 65% possibility on the upper limit.
Sergeant, we need to make this work.
Do you understand?
We are locked into this kill chain.
We have to make a decision. There are...
There are many lives at risk.
Ma'am.
I think...
I think if I make this
the point of impact, then...
There I could predict
a 45% possibility of fatality.
- That might be possible.
- 45%?
- Possibly.
- Good man. Good man.
I'll put that to Cobra.
Ma'am.
It's just an estimate.
Yes, of course. Of course, I understand.
In these circumstances, any calculation
can only be a speculation.
Don't worry.
This puts you beyond any culpability.
Thank you. Thank you, Sergeant.
Thanks, ma'am.
Sir, I have a revised assessment
from the targeteer.
If you would look at the diagram.
By targeting the missile here,
there is an estimated
45% chance of fatality
in this area here,
where the girl is positioned.
We have now done everything in our power
to give this girl a chance to survive.
Thank you, Colonel.
Minister.
Do we have authority
to prosecute the target?
- 45%?
- 45%.
Yes.
You may proceed.
Ma'am.
Lieutenant Watts, we have rerun the CDE.
You are authorized
to prosecute the target.
My targeteer is sending
through the adjusted DPI.
Engage now. Am I clear?
Yes, Colonel.
Cleared to engage.
Running the dash 34 checklist.
Carrie, call when ready.
Ready.
Weapon systems on.
Laser sensor?
Check.
- Gimbal?
- Released.
Slant range set.
System power, nominal.
Designated power, nominal.
Missile?
Coded.
Mean altitude set to standard.
GPS signal...
Check.
Satellite 1 lock?
Satellite 2 lock?
Check.
Arm weapon.
Weapon status.
Check.
Three, two,
one.
Rifle, rifle, rifle. Weapon away.
Time of flight, 50 seconds.
There's a boy!
Oh, shit!
Wait, he's buy... He's buying the bread.
Forty seconds.
Come on, come on, come on.
Go!
She's moving.
Zoom in. We need to know
that we've hit our targets.
Yes, Colonel.
Steve, identify the bodies.
Zoom in.
Body identified as probably Rasheed Hamud.
Body unknown, but likely Abdullah Al-Hady.
We need to re-engage.
Colonel!
We're going again.
She's on the list.
Lieutenant.
Yes, ma'am.
Target the moving body.
Engaging target.
System is still green.
Ready on the red missile.
Target is captured.
Three, two,
one.
Rifle, rifle, rifle. Weapon away.
Time of flight, 50 seconds.
Alia.
Steve, you need to get us close in
on the remains of Danford.
Yes, sir.
Carrie, we need to go identify the body.
Based on the footage I'm seeing,
body confirmed as Susan Helen Danford.
Benson.
Mission accomplished.
Well done, Katherine.
Thank you, sir.
I'm sorry, Sadd,
I couldn't see any other option.
Yes, ma'am, I understand that.
Now, you will file
your report as a 45% CDE.
Understood?
Sadd?
45%.
Yes, Colonel.
In my opinion, that was disgraceful.
And all done from
the safety of your chair.
I have attended the immediate aftermath
of five suicide bombings
on the ground, with the bodies.
What you witnessed today
with your coffee and biscuits
is terrible.
What these men would've done
would've been even more terrible.
Never tell a soldier
that he does not know the cost of war.
Sir.
Oh...
Thank you, Captain.
You did well. Both of you.
Thank you, sir.
You should go home. Get some rest.
I need you both back here in 12 hours.
All right?